A Guide to the Ethel Littlejohn Adams Collection, 1847-1941
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Ethel Littlejohn Adams Collection 1847-1941
Thomas Balch Library
M 091, BV 009, VC 0015
Material from a drugstore in Leesburg, Virginia owned by Armistead R. Mott, followed by Horace C. Littlejohn. Also includes material from the founding and administration Loudoun County Hospital, its management, and records from Littlejohn's service as its treasurer.
Ethel Littlejohn Adams, Leesburg, VA.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Ethel Littlejohn Adams, Leesburg, VA.
Alternative Form Available
None.
Accruals
1988.0001
Biographical Information
Armistead Randolph Mott (1822-1894) was a physician and pharmacist. Though born in Leesburg, Virginia, Mott spent much of his early life in Kentucky. In 1845 he graduated from the Jefferson College of Medicine in Philadelphia and returned to Leesburg to practice medicine and pharmacy. Mott opened a drugstore opposite the courthouse at 5 North King Street and saw patients in an office above the store. Mott married Virginia L. Bentley in 1846 and had several children, including T. Bentley Mott, U. S. military attache and memoirist. During the Civil War, Mott served in the Confederate Army as a medical officer. At the conclusion of his service, Mott resumed his medical practice and worked with a succession of partners in the operation of the drugstore. He eventually moved the establishment next door, to 7 North King Street. Mott died in 1894, but the drugstore retained the name Mott & Purcell until it was purchased by Horace C. Littlejohn in 1919.
Horace C. Littlejohn (1883-1965), a native of Leesburg, was educated at the Medical College of Virginia in Richmond. He was a founder and treasurer of the Leesburg Hospital, eventually known as Loudoun County Hospital. Littlejohn began his career as a clerk at Mott & Purcell Drugstore. He purchased the establishment in 1919, and Littlejohn Pharmacy became a gathering place for the community until his death in 1965.
Littlejohn married Ethel R. Thomspon (1886-1936). His daughter, Ethel Littlejohn (1917-2006), graduated as valedictorian of Leesburg High School and received a bachelor's degree from Duke University. Ethel returned to Loudoun County where she taught French, English, history, math, and physical education. She married Stephen Hawpe Adams (1912-1997) in 1944, and they had two daughters. Ethel served on The Ladies Board of Loudoun Hospital and was active in the Leesburg United Methodist Church.
Scope and Content
This collection contains a variety of materials that belonged to Armistead Randolph Mott and Horace C. Littlejohn. A few items belonged to Ethel Littlejohn Adams. Much of the material from A. R. Mott concerns the operations of the drugstore and his medical practice. His day books contain lists of appointments, and the prescription ledgers are made up of prescribed compounds pasted to ledger pages. His material also includes three bills of sale of slaves, Mott's oath of allegiance to the U.S. government, and an application for pardon after the Civil War. In addition, there is a farm book from Rokeby that contains payment accounts for several African American workers on the farm. Mott managed Rokeby in his wife's name, who inherited it from her father.
Littlejohn's material contains prescription ledgers and receipt books as well, but is primarily made up of information about the founding of Loudoun County Hospital, its management, and records from Littlejohn's service as its treasurer. Also included are the minutes from the Leesburg chapter of the Children of the Confederacy, of which Ethel Littlejohn and her sister were charter members. Among the bound volumes is a ledger from the shop of Thomas C. Morallee, Merchant Tailor and Dealer in Men's Furnishings, Goods, etc., an establishment that operated in downtown Leesburg during the 1850s and 1860s.
There are seventeen visual items, thirteen photographs and four postcards. Twelve photographs depict scenes of Leesburg and one of Purcellville. Two of the photographs identify Underwood & Underwood as the photographer. The postcards depict scenes of Harpers Ferry, West Virginia.
Arrangement
Box: folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Albertype Company Photographs (Collection V-18), The Historical Society of Pennsylvania. (accessed October 19, 2013). http://hsp.org/sites/default/files/legacy_files/migrated/findingaidv18albertype.pdf
"Ethel L. Adams." Loudoun Times Mirror, November 15, 2006, Obituaries, A10.
Find a Grave, www.findagrave.com (accessed October 18, 2013).
"Horace C. Littlejohn, 81, Pharmacist in Leesburg." Loudoun Times Mirror, January 21, 1965, Obituaries, A10.
"Leesburg Doctor." The Mirror, 25 January 1894, p. 3.
"Miss Littlejohn Becomes Bride of S.H. Adams." Blue Ridge Herald, August 24, 1944, A1.
Smith, Kathryn Gettings. Exploring Leesburg: Guide to History and Architecture. Town of Leesburg, 2003.
Underwood & Underwood. Collection, 1899-1908. Special Collections Research Center, University of Chicago Library. http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/scrc/findingaids/view.php?eadid=ICU.SPCL.UNDERWOOD
Other Finding Aid
Past Perfect Catalog records
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
The Ladies Board of Loudoun Inova Hospital (M 049), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.; T. (Thomas) Bentley Mott & Georgette Saint Paul Wedding Invitation 23 May 1923 (SC 0062), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Contents List
  - A. R. Mott
    - Account book, 1851-1852
    - Account book, 1873
    - Account book, 1874-1876
    - Account of James F. Devine, 1849-1853
    - Application for pardon and release of property from confiscation (with character reference from C. C. Auger), 25 June 1865, 6 September 1865
    - Bill of sale, Robert Bentley to Virginia L. Mott, 2 slaves (Philip and Esther), 1848
    - Bill of sale, Verlinda Perry to Armistead R. Mott, 1 slave (Mary), 11 July 1849
    - Bill of sale, G. Washington Ball to Armistead R. Mott, 1 slave (Julia), 26 November 1851
    - Correspondence with Daniel G. Smith regarding purchase of property in Leesburg, 1853-1854, 1868
    - Day book, July 1864-February 1865
    - Day book, August 1868-September 1868
    - Day book, October 1869-February 1870
    - Day book, March 1870-September 1870
    - Day book, April 1871-September 1871
    - Day book, November 1871-April 1877
  - A. R. Mott
    - Day book, April 1872-December 1872
    - Day book, January 1873-September 1873
    - Day book, July 1881-October 1881
    - Day book, January 1890-December 1890
    - Financial papers, n.d.
    - Financial papers, 1847-1849
    - Financial papers, 1850-1859
    - Financial papers, 1860-1869
    - Financial papers, 1870-1879
    - Financial papers, 1880-1884
    - Notebooks, n.d.
    - Oath of Allegiance, 20 May 1865
    - Obituary for A. R. Mott, 1894
    - Pharmacy sales book, 1872-1874
    - Rokeby Farm book, 1873-1875
    - Stonemason's account book, 1874
    - Survey of Leesburg by Lemuel Norris, n.d
  - Loudoun County Hospital
    - Annual report, 31 May 1927
    - Articles of Incorporation and amendment, 1912, 1914
    - Bank book and account information, 1913-1924
    - Financial statements, 1920-1941
    - Financial ledger (loose material, see BV 009), 1926-1941
    - Purchase of land, n.d., 1916
    - Record Book of the Board of Directors (loose material, see BV 009), 1912-1916
    - Stock certificate, 1917
    - Tax return, 1925
    - Children of the Confederacy, Minutes of the States' Rights Chapter, 1924-1926
    - Leather wallet that belonged to A. R. Mott
  - Loudoun County Hospital, financial ledger, 1927-1941
  - Loudoun County Hospital, record book of the Board of Directors, 1912-1916
  - Thomas C. Morallee "Merchant Tailor and Dealer in Men's Furnishings, Goods, etc," ledger, 5 March 1860-12 June 1861
  - Mott and Metzger, Receipt book for goods purchased, 16 May 1867-29 March 1871
  - Prescription ledger, 3 February 1865-17 August 1889
  - Prescription ledger, 17 August 1889-30 January 1891
  - Prescription ledger, June 1892-28 November 1893
  - Prescription ledger, 29 November 1893-29 November 1899
  - Prescription ledger, 21 November 1896-4 July 1898
  - Prescription ledger, 1 December 1899-20 October 1900
  - Prescription ledger, 21 October 1900-15 February 1902
  - Prescription ledger, 10 June 1903-27 April 1909
  - Prescription ledger, 30 April 1904-28 August 1905
  - Prescription ledger, 29 August 1905-4 January 1907
  - Prescription ledger, 5 January 1907-21 July 1908
  - Prescription ledger, 21 July 1908-28 February 1910
    - Old Court House, Leesburg, Va., 1890 ca.
    - Morven Park, Home of Ex. Governor Westmoreland Davis, Leesburg, Va., 1890 ca.
    - Peoples National Bank, 1890 ca.
    - Peoples National Bank, 1890 ca.
    - Peoples National Bank, 1890 ca.
    - Old Clerk's office, Leesburg, Va., 1890 ca.
    - [composite photo: at King and Market, looking north on King; S King St at South St; at King and Market, looking east on Market], 1900 ca.
    - Washington's HQ, so they say, 1910 ca.
    - [Loudoun County Courthouse in the snow with passersby], 1910 ca.
    - View from Court House showing Confederate Monument and Peoples National Bank, Leesburg Va., 1910 ca.
    - Jefferson Rock, Harper's Ferry, WV [Postcard], 1910 ca.
    - The Harper House, Built 1860, by Robert Harper, the Founder of Harpers Ferry [Postcard], 1910 ca.
    - View of the Gap from Hill Top House [Postcard], 1910 ca.
    - Looking Down the Gap from Marist Hill [Postcard], 1910 ca.
    - [Purcellville parade], 1915
    - [Littlejohn's drugstore interior], 1920 ca.
    - Littlejohn Drug Store [exterior], 1925 ca.